ILGWU Local 105 Records 5780/053
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
ILGWU Local 105 Records
1939-1972
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union (ILGWU). Local 105
International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union
5780/053
4.28 cubic feet
4.3 linear ft.
Correspondence, reports, minutes.
The collection of Local 105 materials consist primarily of routine correspondence, reports, and minutes of executive and membership meetings.
3781606
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
B. Walker, October 16, 2008
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, April 08, 2019
Biographical / Historical
The International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union was once one of the largest labor unions in the United States founded in 1900 by local union delegates representing about 2,000 members in cities in the northeastern United States. It was one of the first U.S. Unions to have a membership consisting of mostly females, and it played a key role in the labor history of the 1920s and 1930s. The union is generally referred to as the "ILGWU" or the "ILG". The ILGWU grew in geographical scope, membership size, and political influence to become one of the most powerful forces in American organized labor by mid-century. Representing workers in the women's garment industry, the ILGWU worked to improve working and living conditions of its members through collective bargaining agreements, training programs, health care facilities, cooperative housing, educational opportunities, and other efforts. The ILGWU merged with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union in 1995 to form the Union of Needle trades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE). UNITE merged with the Hotel Employees and Restaurant Employees Union (HERE) in 2004 to create a new union known as UNITE HERE. The two unions that formed UNITE in 1995 represented only 250,000 workers between them, down from the ILGWU's peak membership of 450,000 in 1969.
Biographical / Historical
Local 105, International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union (ILGWU), also known as the Snowsuits, Ski Wear, Leggings, Infants and Novelty Sportswear Union, was based in New York City. It represented workers employed in various specialty garment shops in the New York area.
Scope and Contents
The Local 105 materials consist primarily of routine correspondence, reports, and minutes of executive and membership meetings. Much of the correspondence is from Martin L. Cohen, the manager-secretary of Local 105.
The first series consists of meeting Minutes for the Executive Board as well as various Committees including the Appeals, Campaign, Election and Objection, Finance, Grievance Board, Membership, Negotiation, Political and Educational. The Shop Representative meetings include a report from Manager Cohen. The Complaint logs list the complaint against specific firms, as well as disposition, whether the firm agreed to the charges or the complaint was sent to the Impartial Chairman.
The second series consists of correspondence arranged alphabetically by subject. The bulk of the material deals with administrative matters, contract negotiations, donations to (and requests for donations from) charitable organizations, health, welfare and retirement benefits, garment manufacturers, other ILGWU departments and locals, and relations with the AFL-CIO. Some of the correspondence addresses the changing ethnic makeup of the union's membership, particularly the steady increase in Hispanic workers during the 1950s and 1960s. Other items concern the adoption of children orphaned after World War II. A small amount of Martin Cohen's personal correspondence is also included. Significant organizations represented include the AFL-CIO (including correspondence with George Meany), City of Hope, Histadrut, the Jewish Daily Forward, the Jewish Labor Committee, and the New York Cloak Joint Board (ILGWU).
At the end of the collection there are posters that were created by the local to be displayed in the shops and factories. The posters advertise the benefits of membership and dues, the Union Health Center, holiday pay, severance pay, overtime pay, new contract benefits, and information on filing complaints. Some of the posters also include Spanish.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5780: ILGWU records 5780/053 AV: ILGWU Local 105 Audio Recordings 5780/053 P: ILGWU Local 105 Photographs
Arrangement
Series I: Minutes, Executive and Membership Meetings: 1939-68.
Series II: Correspondence, 1939-1970.
Forv?ert?s (New York, N.Y.); Adoption -- New York (State) -- New York; Clothing workers -- Labor unions -- New York (State) -- New York; Collective bargaining -- Clothing industry -- New York (State) -- New York; Health insurance -- New York (State) -- New York; Hispanic Americans -- Employment -- New York (State) -- New York; Labor unions -- Officials and employees; Labor unions -- Charitable contributions; Local union locals.; Orphans.; Pension trusts -- New York (State) -- New York; Women's clothing industry -- New York (State) -- New York; World War, 1939-1945 -- Children; Cohen, Martin L.; Meany, George, 1894-; AFL-CIO.; City of Hope National Medical Center (U.S.).; Histadrut ha-kelalit shel ha-?ovdim be-Erets-Yisra'el.; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. Local 105 (New York, N.Y.); International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. New York Cloak Joint Board.; Jewish Labor Committee (U.S.)
3781606
- Series Series I: Minutes, Executive and Membership Meetings: 1939-68.
  - Executive Board Minutes., 1939-1941 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Dec. 4, 1939 - Dec. 2, 1941. Contains some Yiddish.
  - Executive Board Minutes., 1947-1948 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Feb. 11, 1947 - Nov. 30, 1948.
  - Executive Board Minutes., 1949 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Jan. 11, 1949 - Nov. 9, 1949.
  - Executive Board Minutes., 1949-1950 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Jan. 10, 1949 - Dec. 11, 1950.
  - Executive Board Minutes., 1956 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Jan. 10, 1956 - Dec. 18, 1956.
  - Executive Board Minutes., 1957 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Jan. 8, 1957 - Dec. 17, 1957.
  - Executive Board Minutes., 1958 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Jan. 7, 1958 - Dec. 30, 1958.
  - Executive Board Minutes., 1959 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Jan. 13, 1959 - Dec. 8, 1959.
  - Executive Board Minutes., 1960-1962 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Jan. 5, 1960 - Dec. 11, 1962.
  - Executive Board Minutes., 1963 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Jan. 8. 1963 - Dec. 17, 1963.
  - Executive Board Minutes., 1964 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Jan. 7, 1964 - Dec. 22, 1964.
  - Executive Board Minutes., 1965 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Jan. 5, 1965 - Dec. 28, 1965.
  - Executive Board Committee Meeting., 1966 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Jan. 13, 1966 - Dec. 27, 1966.
  - Appeals Committee Minutes., 1959 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    June 28, 1959.
  - Campaign Committee Minutes., 1960 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    July 12, 1960.
  - Election and Objection Committee Minutes., 1965 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Feb. 2, 1965.
  - Finance Committee Minutes., 1957-1968 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Aug. 22, 1957 - Nov. 4, 1968.
  - Grievance Board Minutes., 1958 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Oct. 2, 1958.
  - Grievance Committee Minutes., 1963 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Mar. 12, 1963.
  - Installation of Officers., 1959 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Mar. 3, 1959.
  - Installation of Officers Minutes., 1962 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Mar. 20, 1962.
  - Membership Minutes., 1959 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Feb. 10, 1959.
  - Membership (General) Minutes., 1961-1964 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Mar. 21, 1961 - Mar. 19, 1964. Contains some in Spanish. See Box 1, folder 52 for second copy.
  - Membership (General) Minutes., 1964 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Mar. 19, 1964.
  - Membership Committee Minutes., 1964-1967 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    Oct. 26, 1964 - Aug. 14, 1967.
  - Membership Committee (General) Minutes., 1965 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Oct. 7, 1965.
  - Negotiating Committee Minutes., 1960 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Oct. 7, 1960 - Oct. 20, 1960.
  - Negotiation Minutes., 1964 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    Mar. 17, 19664.
  - Political and Educational Committee Minutes., 1960 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    Feb. 18, 1960.
  - Shop Representative Minutes., 1957 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    Feb. 27, 1957 - June 27, 1957.
  - Shop Representative Minutes., 1958 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    Apr. 10, 1958.
  - Shop Representative Minutes., 1959 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    Jan. 6, 1959 - July 1, 1959.
  - Shop Representative Minutes., 1960 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    Jan. 14, 1960 - July 19, 1960.
  - Shop Representative Minutes., 1961 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    Jan. 12, 1961 - Mar. 2, 1961.
  - Shop Representative Minutes., 1962 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    Jan. 25, 1962 - Apr. 26, 1962.
  - Shop Representative Minutes., 1963 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    June 27, 1963.
  - Shop Representative Minutes., 1964 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    May 19, 1964 - Dec. 3, 1964.
  - Shop Representative Minutes., 1965 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    Jan. 28, 1965 - Dec. 2, 1965.
  - Shop Representative Meeting., 1966 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    Jan. 27, 1966 - Nov. 3, 1965.
  - Special Committee Minutes., 1957 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    Dec. 2, 1957.
  - Special Committee Minutes., 1958 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    Dec. 1, 1958.
  - Special Committee Minutes., 1959 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    Feb. 5, 1959.
  - Complaint and Disposition Log., 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    Oct. 3, 1958 - July 23, 1959.
  - Complaint and Disposition Log., 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    May 28, 1959 - Jan. 26, 1960.
  - Complaint and Disposition Log. [folder 1 of 2], 1960 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    Jan. 29, 1960 - May 11, 1960.
  - Complaint and Disposition Log. [folder 2 of 2], 1960 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    May 12, 1960 - Oct 18, 1960.
  - Complaint and Disposition Log., 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    Oct. 18, 1960 - Feb. 8, 1961.
  - Complaint and Disposition Log. [folder 1 of 2], 1961 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    Feb. 8, 1961 - July 5, 1961.
  - Complaint and Disposition Log. [folder 2 of 2], 1961 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    July 7, 1961 - Dec. 28, 1961.
  - Complaint and Disposition Log., 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    June 6, 1961 - May 14, 1962.
  - Complaint and Disposition Log., 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    May 16, 1962 - Jan. 7, 1963.
  - Membership (General) Minutes. [2nd copy], 1961-1964 (Box 1, Folder 52)
    Mar. 21, 1961 - Mar. 19, 1964. Contains some in Spanish. See Box 1, folder 23 for first copy.
- Series Series II: Correspondence, 1939-1970.
  - Adopted Children (War Children), 1940-1952 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - AFL-CIO, 1952-1970 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - B'nai B'rith Sports Lodge, 1959-1963 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - City of Hope, 1948-1966 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Contributions, 1963-1966 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Incl. agreements w. institutions requesting charity.
  - Conventions, Union, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Eastern Region (Eastern Out-of-Town Dept.), 1950-1966 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - El Diario, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    Article by reporter assigned to interview Hispanic members & officers of the Union.
  - Ethnic Composition of Membership, 1950-1969 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Financial Reports, 1950-1963 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Firms, 1943-1960 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Incl. Williams Sportswear, Inc. & Wilson Togs, Inc.
  - Firms, 1955-1966 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    Yonkers Casuals Corp.
  - Firms, 1939-1965 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    Incl. Young Set Sportogs, Inc.
  - Guantes Hispanos, 1960-1962 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    Spanish (Golden) Gloves w. Union. participation in sport.
  - Guantes Latinos, 1966-1967 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    Latin Gloves, sponsored by El Tiempo w. Union participation.
  - Hatters, Cap and Millinery Workers Int'l. Union, United, 1952-1958 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    Incl. Alex Rose correspondence.
  - Health, Welfare and Retirement (Vacation) Benefits Funds, 1945-1962 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    I.c.w. Adolph Held.
  - Health, Welfare and Retirement Benefits Funds, 1941-1957 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    Cont'd. Incl. Appeal Committee.
  - Health, Welfare and Retirement Benefits Funds, 1952-1954 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    Cont'd. Incl. Sick Benefits Comm.
  - Health, Welfare and Retirement Benefits Funds, 1947-1963 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    Cont'd. Incl. financial reports.
  - Health, Welfare and Retirement Benefits Funds, 1966-1972 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    Louis Rolnick, correspondence.
  - Histadrut, 1962-1964 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Infants' and Children's Coat Association, Inc, 1946-1960 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    Incl. correspondence. re negotiations.
  - Infants' and Children's Coat Association, Inc, 1961-1962 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Inter-Office Communications, 1962-1966 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - ILGWU, Retirement and Special Assistance Funds, 1966-1967 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Jewish Daily Forward, 1947-1966 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Jewish Labor Committee, 1951-1956 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Jurisdictional Disputes, 1956-1961 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Labor Day Parades, 1960-1963 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Locals 22, 23, 23-25, 62, 66 and 10, 1945-1965 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Locals 89, 91, 99, 1947-1962 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Locals 102, 117, 155 and Dressmakers' Joint Council, 1940-1965 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Locals, Miscellaneous, 1946-1966 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Local 153, Office Employees' Int'l. Union, 1946-1966 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - March of Dimes, 1951-1958 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - March on Washington, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1940-1965 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Negotiations, 1955-1967 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Negotiations, 1967-1970 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - New York Cloak Joint Board, 1946-1964 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Releases, Statements and Articles, 1948-1964 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Shop Representative Meetings, 1952-1966 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Staff Meetings and Related Matters, 1955-1966 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - United States Committee for Sports in Israel [folder 1 of 2], 1962-1970 (Box 7, Folder 5a)
  - United States Committee for Sports in Israel [folder 2 of 2], 1962-1970 (Box 7, Folder 5b)
  - Wolf and Schulman, Accountants, 1952-1962 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Cohen, Martin L., 1970 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    Personal.
  - Photographs. (Box 7, Folder 8)
    Two photographs. One is a montage of 12 posters. One is a group photograph of 8 individuals (7 women and one man).
  - Posters. (Box 2, Folder All)
    English and Spanish. 50 posters.
  - Posters, 1967 (Box 8, Folder 1)